Well, Little Kitty,
if you really want to learn how to catch flies,
you've got to study the masters
like the Venus Flytrap!
Wait, plants can catch flies?
Oh yes!
So, let me answer your question
with another one
"How does a Venus Flytrap work?"
Zoom in!
When you think of deadly predators,
you might Imagine lions stalking the savanna
or sharks patrolling the deep.
But what if I told you
ne of nature's sneakiest killers
just sits there... waiting?
Meet the Venus flytrap
a small but mighty carnivorous plant
only in a tiny patch of the Carolinas. found
It's famous for it's snap-trap jaws
alld d lasre of unsuspecting bugs.
But how does it pull off it's silent ambush?
Well, it all starts with its trap
it kind of looks like a green mouth
lined with pointy, spiky teeth-
On each lobe of the trap,
there are tiny hairs
three on each s
arranged d in a triangle.
These hairs are like the plant's motion sensors.
Ihe moment Q bug bumps into one,
zips through the plant, an electric signal
an electric signal zips through the plant,
kind of like a plant-sized brainwave.
W.. plant-sized brainwave kind of like a
But this trap is clever
it doesn't close right away
It waits.
Yes, that's because snapping shut
takes a lot of energy, and the Venus flytrap
doesn't want to waste it
on something like a raindrop
or a falling leaf.
So, to f figure out if it's caught real prey,
So, to figure out if it's caught real prey.
it waits 20 to 30 seconds
to see if the bug touches a second hair.
And then - BAM!
The trap snaps shut
in just 100 milliseconds
faster than you blink.
Once it's closed,
those jagged teeth on the edges
lock together like prison bars,
bars, prison like lock together
lock Togetner like prison n bars,
holding the poor bug in.
Sirdggles to get out,
it keeps triggering the hairs,
and that tells the trap to
clamp down even tighter.
After an hour or two of this buggy battle,
the trap seals completely.
and now the real digestion starts.
Then, the Venus flytrap
releases a mix of enzymes
think of them like plant stomach acids
acids stomach plant like them jo think
that slowlv break dewn th.
insides of its prey
into a sort of bug soup.
over Ine Next 5 to I2 aays,
Ir siurps up all those nutrients like a smoothie,
leaving behind nothing but a dry,
rinklv exoskeleton
#no falls which eventually
Cir evenfuallyfalls out
yfalls out which eventually
kelue[jrap reopens
Then, with a casual stretch,
the trap gets ready for the next
unlucky customer.
I know, it's kind of hard
not to feel bad for the bug
But the truth is. the Venus flvtra
needs to eat this way to survive.
Sure, it still does photosynthesis
regular plant ike
like d reguidr pldnt
soaking up sunlight and turning it into sugar
but the swampy soil it lives in
doesn't have enough of the nutrients it needs.
So for that extra boost, it has to rely
on catching and digesting bugs.
bugs. digesting pup catching uo
It just goes to show in nature,
It just goes to snow in nature,
even the quietest creatures
have their own wild and
clever ways to survive
Did you know, despite the name Venus flytrap.
95% of its diet isn't flies at all?
D sr S iiosily ails, spiders,
and other crawling critters
who made the fatal mistake of wandering
wandering Jo mistake fatal who made the
into its leafy jaws.
Today's-sketch of the day goes to...
Reeny Loyd Judson!
Hope you learned something amazing today.
Until next time, it's me, Dr. Binocs,
Zooming Out!
Never mind!